### **SUMMARY**

Highly experienced global marketing and business development manager with a passion for web technologies, specifically Ruby on Rails. Proven self-starter with significant entrepreneurial experience and a track record of building organizations, products, and services on a global scale. Hands-on leader who enjoys motivating, training, and guiding teams to ensure consistent results well beyond expectations.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### HISPAND CONSULTING

Scottsdale, AZ & Mexico City, Mexico

### Principal – Global Marketing & Business Development Consultant

2008 - Present

Manage global projects and provide start-up expertise for organizations ranging from fortune 500 to venture start-ups. Lead business development initiatives into emerging markets. Responsible for building fully functional operations that can provide a basis for growth and established market entry. Industry experience includes financial services, technology, education, and mining.

- Created and managed a 150 employee near-shore office in Mexico to provide BPO services to US financial services clients
- Established an 80 person near-shore Mexico contact center for a technology start-up called Perfect Pitch Tech, Inc.
- Structured the conversion of a group of independent insurance agencies with 80K customers into a private insurance carrier
- Developed an organizational performance and productivity system for the largest non-standard insurance agency in Arizona

### AMERICAN INTERNATIONAL GROUP, INC. (AIG)

Dubai, U.A.E & Moscow, Russia

Manager - Global Marketing & Business Development

2006 - 2008

Managed the profitability and performance of accident & health (A&H) insurance products for fifteen countries within the Middle East, Africa, and Southeast Asia (MEASA). Developed bancassurance products and campaigns for banking institutions throughout the MEASA region. Managed vender relationships with government entities, corporations, and institutions. In addition, had responsibility for expanding AIG's Russian Life Insurance organization, totaling 800 agents. Aggressively advanced the growth through operational improvements and the recruitment and development of directors, managers, and agents.

- Designed and established a Worksite Marketing distribution channel for A&H insurance products in the MEASA region
- Grew the total generated sales premium for A&H products in the MEASA region by 60% from the prior year
- Acquired and managed a multi-million product distribution partnership with the U.A.E. Government Transportation Bureau
- Implemented sales strategies and organizational improvements that contributed to a 400% increase in AIG Russia's top-line

### HISPAND CONSULTING

Scottsdale, AZ

### Manager - Global Marketing & Business Development Consultant

2005 - 2006

Executed various business development and market research projects for companies desiring to enter or expand into Latin-American markets, developing projects for companies that ranged from Fortune 500 to small start-ups. Produced business intelligence deliverables that provided insights on local business practices, market trends, and competitive landscape.

- Conducted market research for Dial Corp that increased advertising ROI of Viva laundry soap in the US Hispanic market
- Procured a client base for RSC Holdings that enabled them to expand their service offering into the Gulf of Mexico
- Performed a competitive analysis project that enabled Atlas Copco to increase its foothold within the Mexican energy market

### **EDUCATION**

Thunderbird School of Global Management

Glendale, AZ

MBA in Global Management; International Business Strategy concentration

May 2005

#1 ranked International MBA program by the Financial Times, Wall Street Journal, and U.S. News and World Report.

**Arizona State University** 

Tempe, AZ

Bachelor of Science, Finance; Bachelors of Arts, Italian; Minor, Portuguese

**Dec 2002** 

Federal University of Ceará

Certificate, Portuguese Language and Cultural Studies

Fortaleza, Brazil July 2001

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

**Programming Languages:** Ruby, HTML, HAML, CSS, and JavaScript (jQuery) **Development Technologies:** Ruby on Rails 4, Sinatra, and Rspec(TDD & BDD)

GitHub Coding Repository: <a href="https://github.com/rickcid">https://github.com/rickcid</a>
Code Learning Blog: <a href="http://rrcid.tumblr.com/">http://rrcid.tumblr.com/</a>

### LANGUAGE SKILLS

English & Spanish: Native, Italian & Portuguese: Fluent spoken, proficient written

## GLOBAL PROJECT & TRANSACTION EXAMPLES

### LATIN AMERICA

Hispand Consulting's start-up of Mexico BPO center (150+ employees) to service US business clients, Mexico City, Mexico

- Created an outsourcing operation in Mexico, expanding it into a 150+ person organization in the timespan of six months.
- Personally staffed and managed the operation, recruited and trained senior management team, and conducted monthly leadership, management, and sales training sessions in order to create an organizational culture dedicated service excellence.
- Developed all the necessary processes and procedures to provide insurance policy servicing to insurance agency clients in the US; focusing on policy underwriting and auditing, in addition to providing a sales and customer service call-center.

# Perfect Pitch Technology's Mexico software development operation and call center (perfectpitchtech.com), Puebla, Mexico

- Created and Managed the Mexico operation for Perfect Pitch, a pre-recorded live agent technology built on Python platform.
- Recruited and managed the 80+ employee operation, which included six Python developers that maintained platform updates.
- Acted as the bridge between users and the software developers coordinating necessary software performance integrations.

# Big North Graphite Inc. & Equinox Exploration Inc. mine acquisition in Latin America, Sonora, Mexico & Atacama, Chile

- Procured several small graphite concession holders in Sonora, Mexico and negotiated a consolidation of their holdings in order to package a sale to a Canadian publically traded junior mining company, Big North Graphite (TSX-V: NRT).
- Developed a functioning mining operation in Mexico to process and take to market material from Big North's operation.
- Created a producing mining operation in Atacama, Chile for junior mining company Equinox Exploration (TSX-V: EQX).
- Raised a private placement of \$5M for the acquisition of Equinox Exploration's first non-US based mining resource.

## MIDDLE EAST, AFRICA, AND SOUTH EAST ASIA (MEASA)

# AIG's Worksite Marketing Product development and distribution channel launch in the MEASA region, Dubai, UAE

- Established the Worksite Marketing sales channel for accident and health (A&H) products for 15 countries in the region.
- Worked together with regional underwriter to form the introductory product line and developed country marketing strategies.
- Trained and managed the Worksite Marketing sales teams for each country and collaborated with the MEASA A&H Regional Director to develop an aggressive and results driven compensation structure for each country sales team.

# AIG's MEASA Bancassurance and Alternative Distribution marketing channel development, Dubai, UAE

- Developed business relationships with government entities, corporations, and institutions throughout the 15-country region on order to establish affinity partnerships that would create additional distribution channels for AIG's products.
- Designed and managed credit card marketing campaigns for several regional banks, which included Mushreq Bank, Sharjah Islamic Bank, and Riyad Bank; provided AIG's marketing expertise in exchange for client base access.
- Maintained profitable country marketing campaigns and developed quality standards throughout the value chain; monitored
  customer product take-up and created customer incentives to increase ROI of the various campaigns.

# WESTERN & EASTERN EUROPE

# AIG's expansion of the Russia Life insurance agency distribution channel, Greater Russia Project (GRP), Moscow, Russia

- Expanded AIG's Russian Life Insurance organization from 350 agents to 800 in span of six months by developing and implementing sales effectiveness strategies, organizational process improvements, and agent recruitment programs.
- Formed of a more aggressive and results driven compensation model for the agencies, directed its full implementation, and managed stakeholder buy-in, specifically agency managers and unit managers.
- Designed and implemented an automated performance monitoring system that enabled managers to assess and improve agent sales performance more thoroughly, which resulted in increasing closing ratios by 40% and customer retention by 20%.
- Developed a data driven organizational culture by creating data collection processes, organizing analytical departments, and training junior management in data interpretation and performance management information usage.

# AIG's development and global rollout of Term-Life Product "Life Cover Plus", Athens, Greece

- Responsible for product development and global integration of Life Cover Plus, managing all stages of development; from actuarial, compliance, marketing, and underwriting to managing the milestones leading toward full global integration.
- Coordinated the complex launching into each global region, managed the diverse environments and specific issues encompassing each country, and adopted solutions tailored to facilitate integration.
- Designated global champion for product and responsible for gaining buy-in from regional presidents and country managers.

## **UNITED STATES**

## Absolute Insurance's conversion from independent insurance agencies to a private insurance carrier, Phoenix, AZ

- Consolidated a group of 16 independent insurance agencies in Arizona to form a book of business totaling 80K clients with the intent of forming a distribution channel that would appeal to investors willing to fund the formation of a private carrier.
- · Procured funding for project through private investors and managed sale negotiations with agency owners.
- Developed the processes necessary to create an underwriting and auditing operation for the newly formed carrier.

## AALL Insurance employee efficiency and productivity software platform, Phoenix, Arizona

- Designed and organized the employee management platform for evaluating employee daily performance and efficiency.
- Sourced, managed, and directed a team of developers to produce a web based platform that would be end user friendly.
- Implemented the integration and delivery to the 300+ employee organization, providing training and integration support.